Here are the six reasons that 2025 is
the biggest year yet for small business
acquisition. Number one, silver tsunami.
I can't hear that word again. It's
everywhere and it's redundant. It's been
done. We all know about it, but it's
still worth hesitating over and thinking
about because I have sellers who are in
their 90s. I have sellers who are in
their 80s. I have sellers who are in
their 70s who all thought that they
could do what their generations before
them did and sell their business to the
generation right below them. And that
isn't working because there's a lot of
them. So there there are fewer of the
next generation, but also that
generation is not interested in working
until they're 90. So from about really
60 and up, sometimes 55 and up, people
are not interested in certainly
acquiring. They're looking to divest,
stabilize, and sell themselves. So you
have all of the baby boomers selling to
the next generation and all of those
people not wanting it and trying to sell
to the subsequent generation. So there's
an enormous divide too between the buyer
age and seller age a lot of times. So
silver tsunamis here. It is not slowing
down yet. Millennials, this is number
two. Millennials and Gen Xers want
lifestyle and autonomy, right? They're
not into the corner office. They're not
into the pie eating contest where the
prize is more pie. They want to have a
little self-employment. Um they want to
build their own thing. They don't want
to be governed by other people's rules.
it's part of their whole culture. They
ask a lot of questions. They're more
critical of authority. So, there's a lot
there and they're more inclined towards
self-employment than, you know, the
partnership track. And the other reason
is startup bubble has popped. I'm Sarah
Sharp. I'm a deal attorney who helps
people and buy and sell businesses every
day. I have started out practicing law
about 13 years ago and I represented a
lot of startups over the years. Tech
startups were huge in the 2010s.
Everybody was going to be the Uber for
whatever. um the new Facebook, right?
And everybody was going to go to the
moon. There were a ton of venture
capitalists interested in just basically
investing in an idea. The concept of
accelerators sprung up where people
would go, young people usually in person
and like live in this community where
their idea was nurtured and they were
given access to investors and board
members and advisors and they were
taught all of these things to try to get
their their SAS or their tech idea to
the next level. and there were series A,
series B, series C, right? Um, and a lot
of those companies that sometimes the
same ones I represented at the
beginning, they've dissolved. Um, it
didn't work out. They didn't catch their
moment. Now, a lot of them did catch a
moment that looked really good in the
headlines. I will say, and I think any
other lawyer who does this has had this
experience. When you actually know the
terms of the thing that hit the
headlines, it's usually not as exciting
for the startup founder as it seems. So
that big merger might have been really
nothing more than selling the the email
list and couple assets to somebody for a
couple grand um to save face, but that
it still would make the news. There were
a lot of people chasing these, you know,
ideal one in a million outcomes and that
they saw in the news and some of those
weren't even real. So people know that
now startup bubble has burst. Number
four, search funds, right? searchers and
entrepreneur through acquisition has
slid in to fill the gap on those folks
who maybe if they were in their position
they are now. Um 10 years ago they would
have been all about the tech startup but
now people don't really have the stomach
for tech startup state of the economy
we're in. So they want hedged downside
and entrepreneurship through acquisition
is incredibly appealing because you're
basically buying a cash flowing asset
that will support you while you continue
your entrepreneurial journey almost
immediately. So the downside risk is
much more limited. Now the upside is
pretty limited too compared to going to
the moon with a Facebook or an Uber or
whatever. But I think the generation of
entrepreneurial people that we have
right now are not as deeoeyed or
optimistic about the being the one in a
million to go to the moon. So for them
the capped downside is very appealing.
so they can stretch their
entrepreneurial muscles, implement
everything that they learned in their
MBA program and um also not take on the
enormous risk that people did in the
tech startup. So the fifth reason,
interest rates. So interest rates have
really colored the market in a couple
different ways, but the way I'm talking
about right now is people often don't
trust the markets or they want to
diversify their investment. So if you
have a good job and you've got some
margin and you're trying to be
responsible, of course you invest in,
you know, index funds and things like
that, but you also want to invest in
something else that's not the same as an
index fund because, you know, that feels
smart and that's the rich dad poor dad.
And all of the advice is like yes, do
this, but also do other. Historically,
that would have been real estate. Um,
commercial real estate is like the next
step for, you know, people in their 30s
who have a lot of additional income and
are trying to make smart choices. that
at the current interest rates um
commercial and residential type of like
rental properties and they just very
hard to get them to pencil. So getting
it to pencil means there are very few
deals to be made in real estate right
now because you have such a high
interest rate that the cost of holding
the property. The amount you can rent it
for hasn't like lived up to that yet. So
most deals are only even if they are a
deal are barely profitable. They're not
at the level where you're it's a slam
dunk and there's risk there, right? So
you have to have a lot of capital. you
have to take on pretty big debt and the
rental rates are just not there to have
enough margin to make it seem
comfortable. So, people look elsewhere.
A lot of those people turned to crypto.
Um, crypto was really exciting because
it was for a dollar. You could take a
dollar, you know, the barrier to entry
was so low. You can buy a smallest
fraction of a bitcoin and know that you
have something that is an asset that is
different than the market. But over the
last couple years, the crypto investment
landscape has basically become so
regulated that it now is in lock step
with the stock market. So yeah, it's a
little bit different, but if the US
stock market is up, crypto is up. If
it's down, crypto is down. So it's
really trading and starting to feel a
lot more like a different form of stock.
Um, and it's not really scratching that
itch. So turn to business. Buy a
business. Why not? If you can't buy a
rental property, crypto seems silly.
you've already invested in the stock
market which is like very stressful to
do current economic times in 2025 then
why not invest in something that you
have more control over than any of those
things which is a business. So a lot of
people are coming to the scene as an
investor who is just interested in it as
an economic play and the final reason
essentially live like an entrepreneur or
a self-employed person. A lot of folks
got a taste of that during the pandemic
and they started working from home and
getting to kind of control more pieces
of their schedule.
then they got forced back into the
office or there's threats of being
forced back into the office and that's
just not appealing. Generally speaking,
people aren't really company people like
they used to be. A lot of folks will
move around every year, year and a half
from company to company. Um, and that
can be really exhausting. So, if you're
doing that, it's it's a very natural
thing to say, well, maybe I should seek
self-employment. Maybe I should control
my own destiny in this way. But
especially if you got booted out because
of layoff during the pandemic or you
electively said, "No thanks. I like my
life where I get to hang out with my dog
all day." And I'm not interested in
having to go into your office so that
you can delight an all me with once a
week bagel delivery. If that's your
thing, then buying a business is a
genius way. You could start your own
business, sure, but you're already in
your prime. You might as well buy one so
it's cash flowing on day one, right? And
they're not that different starting a
business versus buying a business to
build. Because if you start a business,
you're basically taking a loan from
yourself. Sometimes you're literally
getting a loan to live on while you
don't have enough money coming in. It's
a timing issue. When you buy a business,
you've got a loan to buy the business,
but you've got money coming in
automatically. So depending on the
numbers, they can be very similar. So
that's why you have so many more sellers
than ever and so many more buyers than
ever just teeing up this like absolute
tons and tons of smaller than ever
business transactions that are raining
down on us in 2025. Hope that's helpful.
If you found this interesting, please
check out dealacademy.org so you can
become the expert on buying and selling
businesses. Um, sign up for our
newsletter if you want to hear about
market trends or subscribe to this
channel so you can keep in the loop.